today I want to share with you the
technique I always use with great
success to beat procrastination and be
more productive in my studies and work
we live in a distracted world and the
devices we use that help us work and
study can also be the ones that distract
us and help us procrastinate the laptop
you use to take notes write code and
build your Empire is the same laptop
that will give you endless entertainment
and distraction the same tool can help
you build your dream and life's work or
help you postpone working on them
forever and ever what I found out is
that even though procrastination is bad
we can actually use it to our advantage
if we deploy procrastination
strategically and leverage a process in
the brain known as the zynic effect we
will be able to beat procrastination
consistently and effortlessly becoming
more productive and accomplishing more
the goal is to stop procrastinating not
by using willpower but by tricking our
brain the zynic effect is a
psychological phenomenon named after the
psychologist and psychiatrist that
discovered it in the 1920s bluma zynic
the zynic effect is everywhere and is
used against us all the time once you
learn about it you will always notice it
the premise of the zynic effect is that
the brain hates open loops and loves
closed Loops let me explain zarnik first
noticed this phenomenon while sitting in
a busy restaurant in Vienna she noticed
that the waiters were very good at
remembering and keeping track of all the
unfinished order even if the orders were
very complex but once the order was
served and completed they seemed to
forget the details almost immediately
after this observation she made some
experiments at her lab where she gave
people simple tasks like solving puzzles
she then interrupted half of the
participants while they were in the
middle of solving a puzzle then after an
hour she asked all the participants if
they could remember what they have been
working on she then discovered that the
people that had been interrupted were
twice as likely to remember the tasks
they have been interrupted on better
than the ones they completed zarnik
discovered that our brains have a need
for completion and if a task isn't
completed it will be more present in our
minds compared to a completed task when
a task is not completed it creates an
open loop that our minds want to close
the Mind does not like open Loops that
is why the end of every episode of a
series always ends up in a sort of Cliff
Hanger to keep people hooked that is why
if you asked someone to watch a 10hour
movie they would say no but if you take
that 10hour movie and divide it on 10
parts each with a cliffhanger at the end
that person will be more likely to binge
watch the whole thing so how do we use
this phenomenon to our advantage and
beat procrastination in the head we have
to do what Ernest Hemingway did Ernest
Hemingway a champion among writers and
Nobel Prize winner used what he called
useful interruptions it is said that he
used to stop his writing sessions right
in the middle of a sentence not page or
paragraph a sentence by doing this he
created an open loop which means that
the next day he will be eager to get
started writing thus defeating
procrastination before it even showed
its ugly head if we have a big project
to work on like Ernest Hemingway had a
book to write we need to divide that
project in small milestones and easy to
accomplish tasks like paragraphs or
chapters of a book and what we have to
do is to make sure that we don't finish
a work or study session after we
complete a milestone instead we have to
make sure we leave a milestone halfway
done if we finish the day with an open
loop it will be incredibly easy for us
to get started the next day and it won't
be because of willpower that we will get
back to work it will be because of that
feeling of incompleteness the open loop
that our mind is dying to close will
give us the push we need to get started
quickly and to not procrastinate all we
have to do is learn how to deploy
procrastination strategically and
postponed finishing a task on purpose
while we are in the middle of it try
this and let me know if you works for
you this tiny trick has done wonders for
me thanks to this technique I don't have
to go to battle with myself every
morning instead I just look forward to
finishing what I started and when I
finish a task early in the day that
gives me a tiny Victory and
accomplishment which gives me a tiny
heat of dopamine and satisfaction early
in the morning which makes me want to
keep going gives me momentum and puts me
on a state of flow I hope that you use
this technique and it helps you as much
as it has helped me that's it for this
video if you found it useful please like
it share it with your friends and
subscribe to the channel and remember
that if you want to learn to code for
free with me all you have to do is click
the link below there you will find free
courses on JavaScript python react react
native go Dart floter and nextjs among
many others for free we have courses for
all levels from beginner to Advanced all
for free click the link below and I will
see you
there see you on the next one
byebye
la